<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info"
  docName="draft-daley-gendispatch-venue-requirements-00" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes=""
  updates="8718" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3">

  <front>
    <title>Review of IETF Meeting Venue Requirements</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-daley-gendispatch-venue-requirements-00"/>

    <author fullname="Jay Daley" initials="J." surname="Daley" role="editor">
      <organization abbrev="IETF Administration LLC">IETF Administration LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1000 N. West Street, Suite 1200</street>
          <city>Wilimington</city>
          <region>DE</region>
          <code>19801</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jay@staff.ietf.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sean Turner" initials="S." surname="Turner">
      <organization abbrev="IETF Administration LLC">IETF Administration LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1000 N. West Street, Suite 1200</street>
          <city>Wilimington</city>
          <region>DE</region>
          <code>19801</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sean@sn3rd.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2023"/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document sets out a series of recommendations and proposals to the IETF Community from
        the IETF Administration LLC following a review of the IETF meeting venue requirements</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>IETF meeting venues are researched, negotiated, booked and managed in accordance with RFC
        8718 “IETF Plenary Meeting Venue Selection Process” <xref target="RFC8718"/>. While this RFC
        was published in 2020, the substantive work was completed in 2018 and since then there have
        been a number of developments that have affected the efficacy of our current model for IETF
        meetings.</t>
      <t>The IETF Administration LLC has reviewed the venue selection in light of these
        developments, primarily informed by its close engagement with the Secretariat staff who work
        on venue selection, and has identified a number of problems and possible solutions, some of
        which it recommends to the community and some of which it proposes.</t>
      <t>Taken together, the changes strip back much of the detail around venue requirements and
        allow for a greater variety of venue models and thereby support a greater range of possible
        venues.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Summary of Recommendations and Proposals</name>
      <ol>
        <li>We recommend replacing the “close proximity” requirement with a “time to walk”
          requirement somewhere between 5-15 minutes.</li>
        <li>We recommend replacing the “one-third” requirement for rooms in the IETF Hotels with a
          “sufficient to meet projected demand” requirement.</li>
        <li>We propose to no longer provide a Terminal Room and direct people to the Lounge
          instead.</li>
        <li>We recommend that the community reopen the discussion on Internet filtering at venues
          and provide us with better guidance by considering four key questions.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>We finish with a discussion on the merits of returning to the same venues that are known to
        work well vs maximizing the number of different venues, and therefore countries, that we
        visit.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Issues, Analysis, Recommendations and Proposals</name>
      <section>
        <name>The “IETF Hotels” / “One Roof” Model</name>
        <section>
          <name>Current Policy</name>
          <t><xref target="RFC8718"/> defines “IETF Hotels” as:</t>
          <blockquote>One or more hotels, in close proximity to the Facility, where the IETF guest
            room block allocations are negotiated and where network services managed by the IASA
            (e.g., the "IETF" SSID) are in use.</blockquote>
          <t>These are distinct from the “overflow hotels”, which are arranged but not reserved, can
            be some distance from the meeting space, and do not receive the IETF network. </t>
          <t><xref target="RFC8718"/> provides the following mandatory criteria:</t>
          <blockquote><ul>
              <li>It MUST be possible to provision Internet Access to the Facility and IETF
                Hotels</li>
            </ul></blockquote>
          <t>It also provides the following important criteria (only listing those directly
            relevant):</t>
          <blockquote><ul>
              <li>The IETF Hotels directly provide, or else permit and facilitate, the delivery of a
                high performance, robust, unfiltered, and unmodified Internet service for the public
                areas and guest rooms; this service is to be included in the cost of the room.</li>
              <li>The IETF Hotels are within close proximity to each other and the Facility.</li>
              <li>The guest rooms at the IETF Hotels are sufficient in number to house one-third or
                more of projected meeting attendees.</li>
            </ul></blockquote>
          <t>Additionally, <xref target="RFC8718"/> contains this preference:</t>
          <blockquote><ul>
              <li>We have something of a preference for an IETF meeting to be under "One Roof"; that
                is, qualified meeting space and guest rooms are available in the same facility.</li>
            </ul></blockquote>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Current Practice</name>
          <t>What happens in practice is that we book a single IETF Hotel (aka a main hotel), with
            enough rooms reserved for one third of projected attendees. Most of the time this is
            under the same roof as the meeting space because hotels often tie their meeting space to
            the size of the guest bedroom block. In other words, in order to be able to book
            sufficient meeting space in a “one roof” venue, we need to reserve a large room
            block.</t>
          <t>The IETF network is made available in the IETF Hotel, covering the guest bedrooms and
            the main common areas. Even when we are not under one roof, we nearly always aim for a
            single hotel to fulfill the requirements of the IETF Hotels. The IETF has only installed
            the IETF network into more than one hotel on a very small number of occasions.</t>
          <t>There are a number of advantages to having a single IETF Hotel:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>It simplifies the negotiation and installation of the hotel network. Very few hotels
              have any experience of a third party installing a network and so the negotiation is
              often as much work as the installation.</li>
            <li>One large room block is more likely to result in a lower room price and hotel
              commissions paid to the IETF.</li>
            <li>For the core group of IETF participants (and staff) that normally stay in the IETF
              hotel or close by, there is a strong sense of community.</li>
          </ol>
          <t>When this hotel is under the same roof as the facility then there are further
            advantages:</t>
          <ol start="4">
            <li>It is usually easier and more flexible to work with a single point of contact
              instead of several (convention centers with separate contacts for AV, F&amp;B, and
              space).</li>
            <li>It can be much cheaper than working with a separate convention center.</li>
            <li>Group discussions can more naturally move from the facility to the hotel. </li>
          </ol>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Developments</name>
          <t>As noted earlier, there have been a number of developments that have affected the
            efficacy of our current model.</t>
          <t>The most recent of these developments was the COVID driven cancellations and lockdowns
            that badly affected the hospitality industry overall. Hotels and convention centers are
            now much more cautious about the terms of their bookings and much less willing to invest
            in order to secure a booking, as they aim to protect themselves from any similar sudden
            loss of income. For example, many hotels are now requiring payment in full in advance
            for guest room blocks from conference organizers. </t>
          <t>The current high global inflation and uncertain economic outlook adds to the risk
            averse stance of hotel and convention centers. </t>
          <t>Then there is the impact of the now ubiquitous offering of short-term apartment rental
            sites. These sites are significant competitors to hotels for traveler accommodation both
            on price and availability.</t>
          <t>Taking a more long-term perspective, the nature of Internet access for travelers has
            changed significantly over the years and the trajectory is much the same. In most of the
            countries that we visit, local SIM cards with a sufficient data limit are readily
            available at a reasonable price. The VPN industry has exploded with many commercial
            offerings and many corporations providing a VPN for staff. In addition, IETF-developed
            protocols like DoH and MASQUE have made protecting DNS and web traffic quite easy.</t>
          <section>
            <name>Hotel Internet Access</name>
            <t>When the NOC adds the IETF network to a hotel, the general approach is to bring in
              new external connectivity via one of a number of mechanisms and then work with the
              existing hotel infrastructure to configure a new SSID on the hotel APs that avoids as
              much of the hotel captive portal equipment as possible.</t>
            <t>Hotel WiFi has improved significantly, both in bandwidth and quality, and there
              appear to be fewer hotels doing silly things such as trying to intercept SSL
              connections. However, the experience of the NOC in working with hotel networks, a
              broader experience than just working with the IETF hotels, is that there remain a
              large number of problems with hotel WiFi. For example, the following issues have been
              encountered by the NOC:</t>
            <ul>
              <li>Access points installed inside elevators to provide a better experience in the
                elevators</li>
              <li>Access points configured to rotate their channel at a frequency of less than a
                minute.</li>
              <li>Captive portals that only allow for a small number of IPv6 connections because
                anything more must be a mistake.</li>
              <li>Networks with plenty of external bandwidth but such a low-powered captive portal
                setup that effective bandwidth per user is below usable.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>In conclusion, while hotel WiFi has improved significantly, it remains entirely
              unpredictable as to how it will hold up when used by a large number of engineers with
              unusual traffic profiles. </t>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Practical Concerns</name>
          <t>This model limits our choice of venue as it tends to exclude “one roof” venues that
            have sufficient meeting space but insufficient rooms, and to exclude those venues where
            there is a convention center that is suitable for us, with a choice of nearby hotels
            that in total have sufficient rooms to accommodate us, but none of the hotels
            individually is big enough to meet our requirements for a single IETF Hotel. In both
            cases, it is not the policy that excludes them but the practicalities of implementing
            the policy. </t>
          <t>The large room block strategy is losing its appeal due a number of factors. </t>
          <t>As noted above, hotels are increasingly wary of reserving large blocks of rooms as they
            used to do, for a number of reasons. </t>
          <t>Where we can get a large room block, we are finding that hotels are less willing to
            provide us good discounts, which means the room pricing is not always on a par with
            other nearby hotels, with a smaller number of available rooms. </t>
          <t>We are reserving more hotel rooms than are being used and the anecdotal evidence is
            that this is down to more people making individual arrangements using short-term rental
            sites. This is exposing us to unnecessary risk as we are required to financially
            guarantee certain levels of occupancy, and is leading to wasted effort. It also means
            that we are not receiving the anticipated commission income from hotels, which would
            anyway be lower than pre-COVID due to the financial caution of hotels. </t>
          <t>Finally, despite the effort that goes into providing the network in the IETF Hotel, it
            should be noted that we understand very little about how it is used. </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Recommendations and Proposals</name>
          <t>We make the following recommendations: </t>
          <ol>
            <li>To replace the “close proximity” requirement for the IETF Hotels with a “time to
              walk” requirement, that aims to limit the time it takes to walk from the hotel(s) to
              the meeting space and to each other. We make no proposal as to the length of time
              other than to note it should not be any less than five minutes nor more than fifteen
              minutes (see <eref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/15-minute_city"/> for context
              and <eref target="https://app.traveltime.com"/> to generate a walking time polygon for
              your city of choice) and that <xref target="RFC8718"
                sectionFormat="of" section="3.2.2"/> already uses a walkability test of 5-10 minutes
              for a similar purpose.</li>
            <li>To replace the requirement for the total room block in the IETF Hotels from
              “one-third of the projected attendees” to a more flexible “sufficient rooms to meet
              the expected demand”. Short-term apartment rental companies only operate in some
              countries, so the number of rooms booked will need to vary depending on our assessment
              of the availability of alternative forms of accommodation. Note, this excludes the
              number of rooms reserved in the overflow hotels, which are not guaranteed and which do
              not benefit from the IETF network.</li>
          </ol>
          <t>We propose:</t>
          <ol start="3">
            <li>For the NOC to monitor the usage of the IETF network in the IETF Hotels in order to
              understand it better. This would provide the data for a review of the hotel network
              and what, if any, changes are needed. We leave the details of what monitoring takes
              place to the NOC and community to decide.</li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>The Lounge, Terminal Room and Ad-hoc Space</name>
        <section>
          <name>Current Policy</name>
          <t><xref target="RFC8718"/> includes the following requirements as important
            criteria:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>There are sufficient places (e.g., a mix of hallways, bars, meeting rooms, and
              restaurants) for people to hold ad hoc conversations and group discussions in the
              combination of spaces offered by the facilities, hotels, and bars/restaurants in the
              surrounding area, within walking distance (5-10 minutes). </li>
            <li>At least one IETF Hotel or the Facility has a space for use as a lounge, conducive
              to planned and ad hoc meetings and chatting, as well as a space for working online.
              There are tables with seating, convenient for small meetings with laptops. These can
              be at an open bar or casual restaurant. Preferably the lounge area is centrally
              located, permitting easy access to participants. </li>
          </ul>
          <t>The only requirements for a Terminal Room are given in the The Tao of the IETF (<eref
              target="https://www.ietf.org/about/participate/tao/"/>), which describes it as a
            dedicated room with extended opening hours beyond the normal hours of IETF meetings,
            Ethernet connectivity, a printer and a staffed helpdesk. </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Current Practice</name>
          <t>The Lounge is a feature of every IETF meeting. It is regularly but lightly used, far
            below capacity.</t>
          <t>The Terminal Room is a feature of every IETF meeting. It is regularly but lightly used,
            far below capacity. It meets most of the requirements from the Tao (<eref
              target="https://www.ietf.org/about/participate/tao/"/>), but the decision was taken
            some years ago to move the helpdesk to the reception area.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Developments</name>
          <t> Almost everybody at an IETF meeting now has a laptop, tablet, or smartphone (if not
            all of these) and WiFi in those devices is ubiquitous. In the other places where people
            regularly work outside of the office (airport lounges, cafes, hotels, etc) cabled
            ethernet connections are a rarity.</t>
          <t>The need to print such things as travel documents, event tickets, and the like, has
            dropped to virtually zero as all of these things have been replaced with apps on mobile
            devices.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Practical Concerns</name>
          <t>Those people that use the Terminal Room rarely use any of the facilities provided; they
            are largely after a quiet place to work between working group meetings they plan to
            attend. </t>
          <t>The demand for in-person technical support is low and almost all of the visits are for
            things that could be supported remotely via a support ticket. The IETF NOC team already
            responds to support tickets throughout the meeting and we specifically monitor the
            perceptions of our support response in our post-meeting surveys.</t>
          <t>In practice, negotiating the requirements of the Terminal Room with the venues takes
            disproportionately long and its usage is too low to justify this work. </t>
          <t>In our last two post-meeting surveys, comments have been made about the lack of ad-hoc
            space in and around the facility, and the positioning of the Terminal Room and Code
            Lounge:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>“the rather limited number of chairs and lounge tables in front of the meeting
              rooms”</li>
            <li>“less space for social interaction and the terminal room/code lounge was far away
              from the meetings”</li>
            <li>“Terminal room: this should have been more readily accessible and not located on
              floor -3 in a room with no window”</li>
            <li>“Hard to find breakout rooms and have the side conversations that are so critical to
              IETF sessions”</li>
          </ul>
          <t>Increasing ad-hoc meeting space presents us with some challenges:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>Most venues include “pre-function” space but we tend to use that for our
              registration desk and related desks (e.g. IANA, RPC).</li>
            <li>There are many venues that could not support such space and if it became a strong
              requirement that would significantly reduce our choice.</li>
            <li>Of those venues that do have such space, our experience is that they often do not
              have the furniture and so we would need to rent it. This is not an insurmountable
              problem but does mean increasing our costs at a time we want to be reducing them. </li>
            <li>Fire restrictions often prevent us from using space that might appear to the
              observer to be otherwise free for us to use in this way.</li>
          </ol>
          <t>Given the under-utilization of the Lounge it might make sense to reconfigure the
            meeting space to make the Lounge easier to access so that it can more easily be used as
            ad-hoc meeting space, but where we have tried that it has meant having the meeting rooms
            further apart and participants have complained about that.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Proposals</name>
          <t>As the Terminal Room is not a requirement from <xref target="RFC8718"/> , it
            is within scope for the LLC to propose the following changes:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>To no longer have a Terminal Room. Anyone that wishes to use the Terminal Room will
              be directed to the Code Lounge instead.</li>
            <li>Drop the in-person helpdesk. Technical support will still be available via the
              support email and we will introduce a new Zulip channel for live support. On those
              rare occasions when in-person support is required, then an engineer will appear.</li>
            <li>Drop the requirement for an IETF provided printer. If people need to print then they
              will need to identify suitable facilities themselves. The registration desk may be
              able to provide pointers, but we are no longer guaranteeing that print services will
              be available.</li>
          </ol>
          <t>Relatedly, the meeting planning team will be taking the following actions:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>Where the opportunity arises for us to provide greater ad-hoc space through rental
              of furniture, then we will consider this.</li>
            <li>We will experiment with the location of the Lounge and see what feedback we get from
              that.</li>
            <li>We will improve the messaging and signage around the lounge, encouraging people to
              use it as ad-hoc meeting space.</li>
          </ol>

        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Internet Filtering</name>
        <section>
          <name>Current Policy</name>
          <t><xref target="RFC8718"/> has a lot to say about filtering:</t>
          <blockquote> As an organization, we write specifications for the Internet, and we use it
            heavily. Meeting attendees need unfiltered access to the general Internet and their
            corporate networks. "Unfiltered access", in this case, means that all forms of
            communication are allowed. This includes, but is not limited to, access to corporate
            networks via encrypted VPNs from the meeting Facility and Hotels, including Overflow
            Hotels. We also need open network access available at high enough data rates, at the
            meeting Facility, to support our work, which includes support of remote participation.
            Beyond this, we are the first users of our own technology. Any filtering may cause a
            problem with that technology development. In some cases, local laws may require some
            filtering. We seek to avoid such locales without reducing the pool of cities to an
            unacceptable level by stating a number of criteria below, one mandatory and others
            important, to allow for the case where local laws may require filtering in some
            circumstances.</blockquote>
          <t>And</t>
          <blockquote>It MUST be possible to provision Internet Access to the Facility and IETF
            Hotels [...] Provisions include, but are not limited to, native and unmodified IPv4 and
            IPv6 connectivity, and global reachability; there may be no additional limitation that
            would materially impact their Internet use. </blockquote>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Developments</name>
          <t>The legal frameworks around filtering have grown more sophisticated and filtering
            technology has similarly developed.</t>
          <t> Additionally, as noted above, VPN technology and other privacy-enhancing technologies
            have also developed rapidly.</t>
          <t>Historically, the IETF has met in countries with significant Internet filtering and
            there is an expectation from the local communities in those countries that we revisit
            them.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Practical Concerns</name>
          <t>In practice the requirements have proven difficult to interpret because they leave too
            many questions unanswered:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>Is any filtering acceptable? For example, some countries operate filters that are
              minimally invasive by redirecting and filtering traffic to a small number of high-risk
              sites and only for one specific illegal activity <eref
                target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_censorship_in_New_Zealand"/> and it
              is not clear if we could meet in a country with such restrictions.</li>
            <li>If we can be reasonably sure that people can legally, technically and practically
              circumvent filtering through the use of VPNs (or VPNs + encrypted DNS, or MASQUE, or
              other) then does it matter what else is going on, on the local network?</li>
            <li>We have historically met in venues where unfiltered access was provided to the
              meeting space and IETF Hotels but not to overflow hotels. Is that acceptable going
              forward?</li>
            <li>There is much text in <xref target="RFC8718"/> about the importance of
              people being able to work in bars, cafes etc yet this is not considered when filtering
              is discussed. Should it be?</li>
          </ol>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Recommendations</name>
          <t>We recommend the community reopen the discussion on filtering and provide us better
            guidance on the key questions listed above.</t>
          <t>It may be that these questions need to be answered on a case-by-case basis when we ask
            for community input on specific venues, but with better guidance we could provide better
            data for the community to consider and minimize wasted effort on venue research.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>New Venues vs Known Good Venues</name>
        <t>The factors that make a venue a good venue are numerous:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Those in common to all participants:</li>
          <li><ul>
              <li>Size and layout of the meeting space</li>
              <li>Facilities in the area around the meeting space</li>
              <li>The weather</li>
            </ul></li>
          <li>Those with a more geographically varied impact on participants:</li>
          <li><ul>
              <li>Overall cost of travel and accommodation</li>
              <li>Visa availability and requirements</li>
            </ul></li>
          <li>Those primarily impacting staff and volunteers:</li>
          <li><ul>
              <li>Service provision from the meeting space</li>
              <li>Technical facilities and service provision</li>
              <li>Local sponsors / hosts</li>
              <li>Desirability for meeting hosts</li>
            </ul></li>
        </ul>
        <t>Revisiting known good venues has a number of advantages and disadvantages:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Advantages:</li>
          <li><ul>
              <li>We know the space and the services work for us</li>
              <li>Participants gain familiarity with the space and can use it more efficiently</li>
              <li>The staff costs associated with researching, booking and managing the meeting are
                lower than negotiating from scratch</li>
            </ul></li>
          <li>Disadvantages:</li>
          <li><ul>
              <li>The venue becomes much less competitive on price (as has happened with
                Prague)</li>
              <li>It restricts the number of local communities that we interact with</li>
              <li>Is it less appealing to Global Hosts to sponsor a meeting in the same venue.</li>
            </ul></li>
        </ul>
        <t>Visiting new venues also has a number of advantages and disadvantages, related to those
          above. However, these are not all equally important. In particular, there are two key
          issues - the availability and requirements for visas, which has a direct effect on the
          breadth of global participation, and the appeal to meeting hosts, which has a fundamental
          impact on the financial viability of IETF meetings. </t>
        <t><xref target="RFC8719"/> is silent on the question of these advantages and
          disadvantages and so the IETF LLC aims to find a balance between the two approaches. The
          community may wish us to take a different approach, or provide further guidance on how to
          balance these various factors.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Next Steps</name>
      <t>Assuming that some changes are worth moving forward with, there are some options for how to
        progress those.</t>
      <t>The first option is a replacement for <xref target="RFC8718"/> with the same level
        of detail as the existing document. That provides for clarity and certainty around the
        requirements and while it will inevitably need replacing as those requirements change, it is
        unlikely that this will be an obstacle to change.</t>
      <t>The second option is a stripped back replacement for <xref target="RFC8718"/> that
        sets the key principles for the venue and leaves the details to the IETF LLC to interpret.
        This has the benefit of avoiding the importance of some meeting features being lost in the
        detail, as arguably has happened with the importance of ad-hoc meeting areas. However, this
        might not ensure sufficient community engagement and oversight of the interpretations of the
        principles.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section. See RFC 8126 for a guide.-->
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have a security considerations section. See RFC 3552 for a guide. -->
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document should not affect the security of the Internet.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8718.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8719.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <t>Thanks to all of the contributors: Laura Nugent Stephanie McCammon, Alexa Morris, Greg
        Wood, Lars Eggert and Jason Livingood</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
